Guide to the Walter Crosby Eells papers 1890-1963
Whitman College and Northwest Archives
Walter Crosby Eells papers
1890-1963
1929-1951
Whitman College and Northwest Archives 345 Boyer Avenue Walla Walla, WA 99362 Archives@whitman.edu https://library.whitman.edu/archives/
Eells, Walter Crosby
WCMss.003
8.5 linear feet 12 boxes
This collection consists mainly of reprints of professional publications by Walter Crosby Eells. Some professional correspondence and scrapbooks are also included.
Collection is open for research.
Donated to the Whitman College and Northwest Archives prior to August 2004. The accession number is retro-0003.
By bound volume.
Walter Crosby Eells was born near Union, Mason County, Washington on March 6, 1886. Eells attended Whitman College, which was founded by his grandfather, Cushing Eells. There he received a Bachelor of Arts, magna cum laude, in Mathematics and Greek (1908) and served as the Editor-in-Chief of the Pioneer. In 1911, Eells received a Master of Arts in Mathematics from the University of Chicago. Between 1911 and 1914 he held teaching posts at Whitworth College, the United States Naval Academy, and Harvard University Engineering Camp. Eells returned to Whitman College in 1916 as Professor in Applied Mathematics (1916-1926) and Education and Educational Statistics (1926-1927). W. C. Eells served as secretary of the Whitman College Alumni Association and editor of the Whitman Alumnus from 1916-1927. Eells received a Ph.D. in Education from Stanford University in 1927 and served as Professor of Education at Stanford from 1927-1938. He was active in American higher education throughout the 1930s and 1940s. He served as the Executive Secretary of the American Association of Junior Colleges and the Secretary of the American Association of Research Colleges. He was also the coordinator of the "Evaluation of Secondary Schools; General Report on the Methods, Activities, and Results" by the Cooperative Study of Secondary School Standards, published in 1939. In the 1945, Eells became Chief of the Foreign Education Division of the Veterans Administration. In 1947, he moved to the War Department to serve as Advisor on Higher Education in the Civil Information and Education Section at General Headquarters for the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers. Eells and other, members of the Civil Information and Education Section worked in Japan through 1951 to establish the post-war Japanese higher education system. Of particular interest to Eells was the suppression of Communist influences and sentiment in Japanese Universities. W. C. Eells was a prolific writer, frequently publishing on mathematics, education, higher education, women in education, and education in Japan and Communist countries in the wake of World War II. He died in Washington, D.C. on December 15, 1962.
The collection consists of 36 bound volumes, including several monographs. It contains both the published and unpublished works of W. C. Eells as reprints, that has been arranged and bound in chronological order. Also contained are clippings referring to W. C. Eells, several scrapbooks and playscripts he created during his time as a student at Whitman College, correspondence, and a student publication titled The Co-op. The collection was bound prior to August 2004.
Items of special interest in the collection include: the correspondence of the American Association of Research Colleges from 1942-1945 (v. 14); correspondence, photographs and survey results created during the formation the Evaluation of Secondary Schools by the Cooperative Study of Secondary School Standards (v. 16-18); the personal journal and photographs of W. C. Eells (v. 13); and Eells' Scrapbook and correspondence documenting his work in post-war Japan (v. 20)
Eells, Walter Crosby
Whitman College. Alumni Association
Washington (State); Colleges and Universities
- Research and other journal articles, 1899-1928; Volume 1 (Box 1)
- Research and other journal articles, 1929-1930; Volume 2 (Box 1)
- Research and other journal articles, 1931-1932; Volume 3 (Box 1)
- Research and other journal articles, 1933-1934; Volume 4 (Box 2)
- Research and other journal articles, 1935-1936; Volume 5 (Box 2)
- Research and other journal articles, 1937-1938; Volume 6 (Box 3)
- Research and other journal articles, 1939-1941; Volume 7 (Box 3)
- Research and other journal articles, 1942-1944; Volume 8 (Box 4)
- Research and other journal articles, 1945-1952; Volume 9 (Box 4)
- Research and other journal articles, 1953-1956; Volume 10 (Box 5)
- Research and other journal articles, 1957-1960; Volume 11 (Box 5)
- Research and other journal articles, 1961-1963; Volume 12 (Box 5)
- Walter Crosby Eells: March 6, 1961 (personal journal and scrapbook), 1890-1961; Volume 13 (Box 6)
- Wartime letters (1942-1945) from the American Association of Research Colleges, Volume 14 (Box 6)
- Bradford Junior College Survey, 1938; Volume 15 (Box 6, Box 14, Folder 14)
- College Teachers and College Teaching, 1957-1962; Volume 16 (Box 6)
- Research College Teachers and College Teaching,Supplement, 1957-1962; Volume 17 (Box 6)
- College Teachers and College Teaching,2nd Supplements, 1957-1962; Volume 18 (Box 6)
- Approved educational institutions in foreign countries from the Veterans' Administration by W.C. Eells Chief of Foreign Education Division Veterans' Administration, 1947 January 27; Volume 19 (Box 7)
- Communism in Education in Japan, scrapbooks and correspondence from W. C. Eells as Advisor on Higher Education, CIE, GHQ, SCAP, Tokyo Japan, 1949 January-1950 August; Volume 20 (Box 7)
- Education in the New Japan, volume 1 Tokyo, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Civil Information and Education Section, Education Division (Walter Crosby Eells mentioned on page 9, v. 1), 1948; Volume 21 (Box 8)
- Education in the New Japan, volume 2 Tokyo, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Civil Information and Education Section, Education Division, 1948; Volume 22 (Box 8)
- Educational progress in Japan, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Civil Information and Education Section, Education Division, 1951; Volume 23 (Box 8)
- Salary and Cost Study of Fresno Schools, Fresno, Calif., Fresno City Council of Education and 1932 scrapbook, Volume 24 (Box 8)
- Surveys of American Higher Education, New York city, Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, 1937; Volume 25 (Box 9)
- Supplementary research and material for writing of Surveys of American Higher Education I. Individual surveys II. Miscellaneous, 1937; Volume 26 (Box 9)
- Evaluation of Secondary Schools; General Report on the Methods, Activities, and Results of the Cooperative Study of Secondary School Standards, Cooperative Study of Secondary School Standards, preface and coordinator W. C. Eells, Kenneth Walter Eells statistician, 1939; Volume 27 (Box 10)
- Evaluation of secondary schools for Cooperative Study of Secondary School Standards: Supplementary materials: I. Development of the evaluative criteria, Early, July 1935-1940; Volume 28 (Box 10)
- Evaluation of secondary schools: Supplementary materials: II. Development of the evaluative criteria, Late, 1938-1940; Volume 29 (Box 10)
- Evaluation of secondary schools: Supplementary materials: III. Reports and records, 1937-1939; Volume 30 (Box 11)
- Evaluation of secondary schools: Supplementary materials: IV. Letters and Forms, 1936-1939; Volume 31 (Box 11)
- Evaluation of secondary schools: Supplementary materials: V. Development of the Manual, 1938-1940; Volume 32 (Box 11)
- Evaluation of secondary schools: Supplementary materials: VI. Committee agenda, 1935-1939; Volume 33 (Box 12)
- Evaluation of Secondary schools: Supplementary Reprints, published by Cooperative Study of Secondary School Standards, 1939; Volume 34 (Box 12)
- Educational temperatures, by Cooperative Study of Secondary School Standards, 1940; Volume 35 (Box 12)
- Religions in Japan, Tokyo, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Civil Information and Education Sect., Religions and Cultural Resources Division, 1948; Volume 36 (Box 12)
- Correspondence, 1903-1960 (Box 14, Folder 2-13)
- The Co-op, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Play, 1908 (Box 14, Folder 15)
- Scrapbooks, 1904-1908 (Box 13, Object 1-5)